Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ב, pe bais,
we're on the דף daf ahead of schedule, ברוך השם. baruch Hashem.
And we pick up on the bottom of פ"א ע"ב. pe alef
amud bais. And we are dealing with the whole issue here
about עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and that not bathing and not putting
on makeup according to the רבנן rabonon is
עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
According to Rabbi Yosi, it's not עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, but it's
דברים שבינו לבינה. dvorim shebeino l'veina. And then the
גמרא gemara had that question about whether it even constitutes דברים שבינו
לבינה dvorim shebeino l'veina for Rabbi Yosi, but it concluded that it
did. And now the גמרא gemara picks up, one minute, right, and
along the way it also underscored the fact that דברים שבינו לבינה,
dvorim shebeino l'veina, again, he can only annul that fact that the
part of it that relates to the two of them, not that
it affects obviously the relationship with other people. So now the גמרא
gemara says like this: We pick up two lines from the bottom
on פ"א ע"ב. pe alef amud bais. בעי מיניה boei minei Rava
me'Rav Nachman. So Rava asked Rav Nachman the following question: תשמיש המיטה
tashmish hamita לרבנן, l'rabonon, עינוי נפש inuy nefesh הוא, hu, או o
דברים שבינו לבינה? dvorim shebeino l'veina? So we asked for Rabbi Yosi
whether not bathing was enough to be considered
בינו לבינה beino l'veina or was it nothing? And we concluded it
was בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. Now asking for the Rabbis, who are
more prepared to identify something as עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, they have
a lower threshold for עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. If a woman
basically prohibits herself to have sex with other people, is the denial
of sex considered to be עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, or is it
considered to fundamentally be about the husband relationship of the husband and
the wife? So the גמרא gemara says like this, again, remember, this
is for the רבנן rabonon that not bathing and not putting on
makeup was עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So what about not having sex?
So the גמרא gemara says like this: אמר ליה, amar lei, so
he said to him, תניתוה, tanisuah, what's bothering you? We taught it
in a משנה. mishna. It says if a woman says, נטולה אני
מן היהודים, netulah ani min hayehudim, that I am removed from Jews,
meaning that basically she is saying I cannot get pleasure from Jews
and specifically here meaning sexual pleasure. So she is denying herself sex.
Or the other way around?
Or she can't have pleasure from me, right?
All right, right, right, okay, thank you, yeah. שעסרה הנאת תשמישה עליה,
she'asra hana'as tashmisha aleha, so the ר"ן Ran says no. It means
their, anyway, we'll see that when we get to it, but anyway,
she's forbidden sex with all other Jews. So it says יפר חלקו,
yafar chelko, that he annuls his portion of it, the fact that
at least means that she can't have sex with him, okay? Which,
right, because again, since it affects him, obviously it has to mean
other people's sexual pleasure is forbidden on her, because she can't make
her sex forbidden on her husband. So she makes all sex from
other people forbidden on her, he annuls his portion, ומשמשתו, u'meshameshta, and
she has sex with him. ונטולה מן היהודים, u'tne'tulah min hayehudim, if
they ever get divorced, then she's forbidden in sex from all other
Jews, okay? Which is going to make it pretty hard for her
to get remarried. So she did it so
he can selectively, well
yes, and we're going to get to that, like can you have
a הפרה במקצת? hafara b'miktzas? Okay, so that's actually what we're going
to get to later today, so hold on with that. All right,
but what we see though is, is that it seems like he
only has power over the fact that it impacts their relationship, not
the, and if it were עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, he would be
able to absolutely, fully annul it. ואי נמי, v'i namai, now he
might not be interested, why should he allow, why should he annul
so that she can have sex with other people? But the point
is not whether he wants it, the point is that it makes
it clear that משנה mishna that he can't, okay? So clearly this
only relates to their,
to בינו לבינה, beino l'veina, it's not seen as a general
עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So the גמרא gemara rejects this. The גמרא
gemara says, לרבנן כי בעי לך, l'rabonon ki ba'ei lach, no, so
that was the question that Rava asked Rav Nachman. Rav Nachman gave
that answer. So Rava seems to say back, that wasn't an answer.
I was asking according to the רבנן. rabonon. משום דנטולה אני מן
היהודי רבי
יוסי קתני לה. mishum d'netulah ani min hayehudi Rabbi Yosi katani lah.
That משנה mishna is Rabbi Yosi. Yes, you're right, that משנה mishna
makes it clear that it's not considered to be עינוי נפש. inuy
nefesh. It's only בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. But that's Rabbi Yosi. And
Rabbi Yosi, as we know, has a much higher standard of עינוי
נפש. inuy nefesh. So for Rabbi Yosi, Rabbi Yosi considers bathing and
makeup not to be עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So he'll consider sex
not to be עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So for Rabbi Yosi, all
it is is בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. But I don't want to
know Rabbi Yosi, I want to know for the רבנן rabonon how
it categorized, what category it's in. Now the גמרא gemara says, what
makes you say that the סתם משנה stam mishna coming up is
Rabbi Yosi? דאמר רב הונא כולה פרקין
רבי יוסי היא. de'amar Rav Huna kula pirkin Rabbi Yosi hi. Aren't
the entire rest of the פרק perek the סתם stam author of
all the coming up משניות mishnayos is רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yosi? That's
a pretty radical statement, right? So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi that has
a very small category of עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, he is assumed
to be the author of the remainder משניות mishnayos of the משנה.
mishna. Why do we assume that? Okay, ממאי, mimai, what's that based
on? כיון דקתני רבי יוסי אומר אין אלו עידויי עינוי נפש, keivan
de'katani Rabbi Yosi omer ein elu iduei inui nefesh, since our משנה
mishna says and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi responding to bathing and what
do you call it, bathing and נו nu and makeup that it's
not עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, למה לי למיסני הרי זה יפר דברי
רבי יוסי? lama lei l'misnei harei ze yafer divrei Rabbi Yosi? He
can annul it because these are the words of רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yosi. Meaning the end of the משנה mishna says רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi says dot dot dot dot dot דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rabbi
Yosi. Why did it have to end with דברי רבי יוסי, divrei
Rabbi Yosi, right? The whole משנה mishna ended with a statement of
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. It says רבי יוסי אומר. Rabbi Yosi omer.
Why does it repeat at the end דברי רבי יוסי? divrei Rabbi
Yosi? So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה מכאן ואילך רבי יוסי
היא. shma mina mikan v'eilach Rabbi Yosi hi. Very interesting read of
the משנה. mishna. Since the משנה mishna ends with repeating דברי רבי
יוסי, divrei Rabbi Yosi, maybe it's almost seeing it as like now
introducing the rest of the פרק perek is דברי רבי יוסי. divrei
Rabbi Yosi. But sort of bringing רבי יוסי'ס Rabbi Yosi's voice to
the
very to the forefront and basically saying like his is going to
be the dominant voice here. So it's a very fascinating assumption the
גמרא Gemara makes. Okay and therefore it says you're right. A later
משנה mishna says he can only annul his part. He cannot totally
make her permissible to have sex with everyone, or whatever, she's married
to him now, but anyway he cannot remove the נדר neder about
denying of sex vis-a-vis anybody other than himself. But nevertheless, that's because
it's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi has a very
small category of עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. The rabbis who have a
bigger category, logically denial of sex should be included in עינוי נפש.
inui nefesh. Okay, so we don't know. It does not have an
actual conclusion, but obviously that does stand to reason.
Okay, so and the ר"ן Ran says if you look two lines
down in the narrow lines, ולעניין הלכה כיון דבעיא ולא איפשטא, u'l'inyan
halacha keivan de'baia v'lo ipashta, our conclusion our question was not resolved.
נקיטינן לחומרא ואינו מיפר אלא דברים שבינו לבינה. nekitinan l'chumra v'eino meifer
ela devarim she'beino l'veina. Yes, we said that the later משנה mishna
is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, but we never were able to clearly
conclude one way or the other about where sex falls for the
רבנן, Rabbanan, עינוי נפש inui nefesh or not. So we'd have to
be strict and assume that he cannot do a generic annulment of
such a נדר. neder. That's his first gambit. He says ואיכא מאן
דאמר, v'ika man d'amar, there is however one that says ונהי דלא
איפשטא הכא, v'nehi d'lo ipashta hacha, here it wasn't resolved, אפילו הכי
איפשטא ליה ממימרא דשמואל דאמר שמואל אבל עונה פלוני עלי מיפר. afilu
hachi ipashta leh m'memra d'Shmuel de'amar Shmuel aval ona ploni alai meifer.
Okay, but some who inferred from a later line that we're going
to come up to with שמואל, Shmuel, we haven't seen that line
yet, so there are some that want to say that even though
the גמרא Gemara doesn't conclude clearly, nevertheless sex is in the עינוי
נפש inui nefesh category. You gotta, you gotta sort of think that's
pretty funny, right? I mean obviously, I mean just to put this
as a small point as a related point, you know like when
there are cases for example that a woman,
you know woman let's say it's a סכנה sakana for a woman
to get married and there's a whole discussion in the גמרא, Gemara,
can she use a מוך, moch, and can she use certain type
of birth control this or that, and like the ראשונים Rishonim point
out like, you know why is the גמרא Gemara and it's trying
to figure out like what איסורים issurim you know maybe you can
be able to get around in order you know or have to
deal with in order for this and everybody says like, well I
don't understand, why not just tell her not to have sex? Or
why not, you know why is why do we assume that she
has to have sex and that but you know even if it's
impossible for her to get pregnant? And pretty much all the ראשונים
Rishonim say because that's of course not an answer. You can't assume
a marriage without, you know the fact that husband and wife are
going to have sex. So
the הלכה halacha cannot say deal with the problem by not having
sex. So clearly, you know it sees sex as very central to
the marriage, you know according to some some ראשונים Rishonim also, we
always talk about a מצוה mitzvah of עונה, ona, some ראשונים Rishonim
say there isn't really even a מצוה mitzvah of עונה ona in
the תורה—I Torah mean עונה ona means something else, it doesn't mean
sex because that's definitional to what marriage is is that the couples
are going to be having sex. So given that, right, it's pretty
funny that it would say that denial of sex is not עינוי
נפש. inui nefesh. However, presumably the point is is that, you know
it's one thing to say that sex is a central and necessary
component of marriage and you can't just say cut it out, as
opposed to saying, you know her איסור issur of herself having sex
with other people, she's not yet married to the other people. She's
married to her husband, right? So to say that the general fact
about, you know of an outside of that context is not עינוי...
inui... you know maybe that's somewhat of the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. Nevertheless,
it is sort of deeply, I think, challenging to think that the
question about a woman not bathing or wearing makeup would be עינוי
נפש, inui nefesh, but denial, you know to be fundamentally not able
to have sex with, you know for the rest of her life,
you know that's not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh.
But she's the one that took the נדר. neder.
I understand, but so did she... then it wasn't a blame. She
also took the נדר neder about bathing and about makeup.
But that was something that could be like physically... I don't know.
There's some women who never... Makeup is עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and
not having sex for the rest of your life isn't עינוי נפש?
inuy nefesh? So the גמרא Gemara doesn't really conclude, you know, but
and it is interesting that the ר"ן Ran brings down a debate,
but my sympathies are with the opinion that whether there is clear
textual evidence or not, just intuitively, to think it's got to be
in the same category of bathing and putting on makeup. Yeah.
I don't recall but what did רב מאיר Rav Meir categorize or
רב יוסף Rav Yosef categorize as עינוי נפש? inuy nefesh?
Like if she can never get, like one of the examples the
משנה Mishna was like to forbid all the fruit of the world
on herself, right? So you mean the difference of like never bathing,
that's not עינוי נפש; inuy nefesh; never eating fruit, that's עינוי נפש.
inuy nefesh. I know you're right, like just holding those up in
contrast. But it's even a bigger question according to the רבנן, Rabbanan,
you know. All right.
Yeah. But what if like a woman really does care about makeup?
Would you really consider that an עינוי נפש? inuy nefesh?
Yeah, so that's the question you asked yesterday that we don't seem
to make differences case by case. We seem to be categorical, which
is also an important question. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay. אמר שמואל משמיה דלוי: Amar Shmuel mishmei de'Levi: כל נדרים בעל
מפר לאשתו חוץ מן הנאה על פלוני. Kol nedarim ba'al meifer le'ishto
chutz min hana'ah al ploni. Husband can annul all vows that a
wife makes, obviously assuming that they're in the עינוי נפש inuy nefesh
category, except if she says, 'So-and-so can't get benefit from me'. Why?
שאינו מפר, She'eino meifer, that's obvious because that's not עינוי נפש inuy
nefesh for her; that's somebody else can't get benefit from her. Okay,
אבל, aval, here's really the חידוש chiddush of שמואל. Shmuel. הנאת פלוני
עלי מפר. Hana'at ploni alai meifer. If she said, 'I can't get
benefit from ראובן'—we're Reuven not talking about sex anymore obviously—if she says,
'I can't get benefit from ראובן', Reuven he can annul it. That's
considered עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So what's שמואל's Shmuel חידוש? chiddush? שמואל's
Shmuel חידוש chiddush is that it's enough that the thing being denied
is a form of self-denial, עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, even if it's
only being denied from one person. Okay, so if for example not
eating fruit is עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, then if I say I
won't eat any of Michael's fruit, it's also in the עינוי נפש
inuy nefesh category. עינוי נפש inuy nefesh is judged not by the
question of: If this vow remains standing, am I going to live
in an afflicted state? The answer to that question is no; there's
a lot of other people out there to give or sell me
fruit than Michael. That's not, but שמואל Shmuel is saying is that's
not how the question is decided. The question is decided: Is the
thing that you are denying yourself, is the denial of that thing,
would that be considered an עינוי נפש? inuy nefesh? And even though,
you know, yes, if I never could have fruit, that would be
an עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So even though I'm only denying it
from one person, it's still in the עינוי נפש inuy nefesh category
and the בעל ba'al can annul it. That's a huge חידוש, chiddush,
right? Such a huge חידוש chiddush because it seems almost exactly against
our משנה. Mishna. Because if you remember, our משנה Mishna distinguished between
this storekeeper and that storekeeper, this country and another country, and שמואל
Shmuel is saying once it's עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, it doesn't matter
if you have another source for it. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא's Gemara not going to be happy
with this based on the משנה. Mishna. ותנן, Utnan, we taught in
our משנה: Mishna: פירות מדינה זו עלי, Peirot medinah zo alai, if
a woman says, 'I can't get benefit from the fruit of France',
יביא לה ממדינה אחרת, yavi lah mimedinah acheret,
bring her from a different מדינה, medinah, and therefore it's not עינוי
נפש, inuy nefesh, he can't annul it because she can always get
from somewhere else. So that's an explicit rejection of שמואל. Shmuel. If
you can get from somewhere else, it's not עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
So אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: דקאמרה שתביא אתה. Dekamrah shetavi
atah. Or the גמרא's Gemara going to say in a minute, שתביא
אתה. shetavi atah. Okay, that basically we now have a crazy reading
of the משנה. Mishna. If he's going to bring it to me,
she has to say... so what she is saying is, she's saying
that, 'I can't get
fruit from this מדינה medinah that you bring, you my husband bring'.
So in that case it's not עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. Why is
it not עינוי נפש? inuy nefesh? Because she can still get the
fruit of that מדינה. medinah. Okay, she's not really denying herself the
fruit of that מדינה. medinah. Now how is that different than the
case where we said before when she said like if she says,
'I won't get benefit from Michael' there,
you know, why is that considered to be עינוי נפש? inuy nefesh?
Okay, so Michael won't give her fruit, somebody else will give her
fruit. Okay, what's the difference? So here I made it a little
bit maybe
imprecise before. If she says, 'I can't get fruit from Michael', that's
not עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, somebody else will give her the fruit.
But let's say what she says is, 'I won't get benefit from
Michael'. Now benefit from Michael, you know, that's not like a physical
object that somebody else could provide her the same thing, right? If
Michael gives her a hand carrying her bags, right, it's not like
well somebody else could give her that hand carrying her bags or
something of that sort. That's
specifically, you know, it's like if it's an object somebody else could
provide the object. If it's the benefit from the person, nobody else
is going to
give her
Michael's help.
But so basically what it boils down to is if the thing,
if the thing, if it's basically a type of a product that
can be provided by somebody else, then it's not עינוי נפש. Inui
Nefesh. But if it's a type of thing that nobody else could,
that that unique specific nature cannot be provided, even if she's not
really in a state of self-denial as a result, it's not like
a million other people could help her with her bags, but nevertheless,
I'm not saying bags, not having help with your bags is עינוי
נפש, Inui Nefesh, but anyway. Okay, but even if she's not in
a state of self-denial,
okay, if the bottom line is that the type of a thing
which is עינוי נפש, Inui Nefesh, that's enough. But if it's something
that basically she's not really even prevented from that thing because it's
an object that somebody else could provide, that's not a problem. So
it's getting very confusing, I acknowledge that,
and but nevertheless here's the basic point. The משנה Mishna seems to
say that if she denies fruit from one מדינה, Medina, that's not
a problem. And here the point is, similar to benefit from Michael,
France fruit, it could be that I could live a totally enjoyable
life having a wide range of different fruits from all different countries,
but I will be, I still will be deprived of one particular
thing, the unique fruit of France. What's a unique fruit of France?
I don't know. Okay, a French baguette. Okay, anyway, it's not a
fruit, anyway, so I can I can vow that that is something
that I'm always denying myself. So the גמרא Gemara says, so why
can't the husband annul it? Okay, that's like, you know, particular הנאת
מיכאל, Hana'as Michael, his French baguette. Your yes, your life can be
total and whole and complete and lovely, but it's a specific thing
that you're totally denying yourself, so why can't the husband annul it?
And the answer is, we re-read the משנה Mishna to say that
actually she only said it was forbidden if it was provided by
the husband. Since somebody else can still provide it for her, she's
not denied French baguette and she's still okay. All right, so now
that's the גמרא's Gemara answer, a very difficult read of the משנה,
Mishna, but the גמרא's Gemara not going to be happy with it.
תא שמע, Tae Shma, come in here, פירות חנווני זה עלי. Peros
Chonvoni Ze Alai.
So she says I can't get benefit from the fruit of this
storekeeper, אין יכול
להפר, En Yachol Lehafer, he cannot annul, because she's not really fully
denying herself. So the גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean she's
not fully denying herself? She's fully, you know, because she can't, there's
no way that she can get the benefit of the fruit of
that storekeeper. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי דקאמר שתביא אתה,
Hacha Nami Dekamar Shetavi Ata,
similar story, that she says that I can't get the fruit of
that storekeeper that you bring, but if somebody else brings it, I
can, so because she's still allowing herself access to it through somebody
else, that's what makes it not a case of self-denial. Okay, again,
totally not פשט Pshat of the משנה. Mishna. Like, the משנה Mishna
does not have this additional demand that it's only a problem if
you bring it. Okay, so now we're going to get to what
the גמרא's Gemara finally going to reject this. If you're having a
hard time understanding what the גמרא's Gemara doing, it's because it's reading
a very hard read of the משנה, Mishna, but don't worry, we're
about to reject it. Okay, then it says like this, לא היתה
פרנסתו אלא ממנו, Lo Ha'isa Parnassaso Ela Mimenu,
if the husband's only provider of food is this storekeeper, in that
case הרי זה יפר, Harei Ze Yafer, he can annul. Right, because
the משנה Mishna basically was against שמואל. Shmuel. The משנה Mishna said,
right, that as long as somebody else you can get, you know,
you're not totally denying yourself, it's okay, but if this storekeeper is
your only provider, then you can annul. Right, we had this, it's
quoting the משנה, Mishna, but it's trying to say it doesn't work
with שמואל. Shmuel. Now you, in order to make שמואל Shmuel work,
you're saying that the whole משנה Mishna is only when she says
that she can't get it when provided by the husband. So the
גמרא Gemara says, well, that doesn't read now because why then would
even if the storekeeper is the only provider, why is it a
problem if all the cases in the משנה Mishna is that she's
saying it's only a problem if you, my husband, provide, but I'm
okay getting it through somebody else? So if that's true, even in
this case of the sole provider storekeeper, she's not totally denying herself
because somebody else could just go to the store and get it.
ואי אמרת דקאמר שתביא אתה, V'ee Amart Dekamar Shetavi Ata, if we're
reading the entire משנה Mishna that she's only denying herself if the
husband is the one who conveys it, so אמאי יפר? Amai Yafer?
Then even if the storekeeper is the only provider, why can he
annul? She's not denying herself that fruit, just have somebody else deliver
the fruit. אלא מדסיפא דלא מייתי בעל, Ela Mide'seifa Delo Maisi Baal,
since the end clearly, since the husband is able to annul, the
case is that she's forbidding it to herself regardless of whether the
husband brings it, that even if the husband doesn't bring it, she's
basically across the board forbidding herself. הוי רישא דקא מייתי היא, Havei
Reisha Dekamaisi Hee, so similarly the רישא Reisha is also whether the
husband brings it, whether she brings it, we don't have this that
she's only forbidding it through the husband. It's clear from the פשט
Pshat of the משנה Mishna that she's forbidding it to herself. of
across the board. Okay. אלא רישא אין יכול להפר, Ella reisha ein
yachol lehafer,
you see in the beginning she cannot annul when she says the
fruit of this מדינה Medinah of France, דקמייתי היא de-ka-maisei hi even
if regardless of who brings it. So basically, we finally just went
through that very complicated thing to get back to the פשט pshat
of the משנה. mishnah. Okay. פשט Pshat of the משנה mishnah is
again that she says, "I cannot get fruit from this מדינה." Medinah.
It says he cannot annul it. Why? Because you can always get
fruit from another מדינה. Medinah. So the question is that's against שמואל,
Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel says if you deny yourself from one type
of a source, even if you have another source, that source is
self-denial and you can annul, but the משנה mishnah says not that
way. You deny yourself from one מדינה, Medinah, you can't annul because
there's other sources. So that is against שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא
Gemara says, "You know what? You're right. The פשט pshat of the
משנה, mishnah, it's against שמואל, Shmuel, but we still have another out.
Guess what the out is."
It's בינו לבינה. de-beino le-veinah. No.
Yeah, good, because it's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So turn the page.
ומתניתין רבי יוסי היא, U-matnitin Rabbi Yose hi, דאמר רב הונא כולה
פירקן רבי יוסי היא. de-amar Rav Huna kulei pirkan Rabbi Yose hi.
Our whole משנה mishnah is רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. ומאי אין יכול
להפר משום עינוי נפש מיפר נדרים שבינו לבינה. U-mai ein yachol lehafer
mishum inui nefesh meifer nedarim she-beino le-veinah. It might be that it's
not עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, it might still be בינו לבינה. beino
le-veinah. That last line is a little parenthetical. The basic answer is
like this: is that
רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yose, remember, had a much narrower definition of עינוי נפש.
inui nefesh. So one place which is narrower is what types of
denials do I call עינוי נפש? inui nefesh? Not bathing, not עינוי
נפש. inui nefesh. You know, not makeup, not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh.
Not having sex, not עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. So the things that
are counted as עינוי נפש inui nefesh is a much smaller category,
number one. Number two, how about this idea of שמואל, Shmuel, whether
it has to be a complete self-denial, you know, totally preventing myself
from getting it or even from one source? So logically, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose would also have a smaller category about that. And for
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose to be עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, it has
to be all fruit from all places in the world. So A,
only certain types of pleasures, of things. And number two, you have
to deny from all sources. But what שמואל Shmuel is saying is
according to the רבנן Rabbanan who include more things—bathing, makeup, maybe sex,
I would hope to say sex
anyway—all of those are עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. They would also say
that even if you're only denying it from one source, that's also
considered to be a form of עינוי נפש. inui nefesh. Okay? So
bottom line is שמואל Shmuel is saying, "You're right, the משנה mishnah
is against me, but again, like the earlier discussion about sex, I
don't care about that. That's רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. I'm going according
to the רבנן. Rabbanan. And I would say for the רבנן Rabbanan
we have a broader definition, not just about the things that are
עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, but that even if it's partial denial and
not total denial, that also constitutes." Another interesting question just to make
you think about, which gets back to the דף daf that Michael
did a few days ago, is what about—so one is who is
the provider, like are you denying it from all sources or just
from one source? How about the duration, right? How about if you
say, right, the גמרא Gemara says that the רבנן Rabbanan call not
bathing for one day עינוי נפש? inui nefesh? Is that specifically about
bathing or would they say that about everything? Once I, because as
Michael's been pointing out, we're dealing with certain formal categories here. We
don't act case by case, right? So if I sort of say,
"Well, formally, you know, bathing is עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, so even
denying yourself from that bathhouse is עינוי נפש inui nefesh even though
there are other bathhouses, because once it's in the category of עינוי
נפש, inui nefesh, it doesn't matter how big the scope is." So
would we say the same about the duration? Right? If we say
not eating fruit is עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, what if I say
I won't eat fruit for a day? What if I say I
won't eat fruit for an hour? What if I say I won't
bathe for an hour? No, I'm serious. Is it just a formal
thing? "Well, once bathing is עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, it doesn't matter
how big is the scope, how big is the time period, formally
it's in that category and you can annul it," right? So I
think that's the question like that needs to be asked. All right,
let's take a look now.
But still, even if according to the גמרא Gemara saying certainly according
to the רבנן Rabbanan this would be an עינוי נפש, inui nefesh,
but even according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose he could still get
him—get her out of it by saying it's בינו לבינה. beino le-veinah.
Yeah, but it makes it more difficult, I got to go out
of my way.
I know, but it's harder to understand why it falls in בינו
לבינה beino le-veinah and there's a little inclination in some of the
ראשונים Rishonim to sort of say, "Well, if we can't get you
in עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, we'll get you בינו לבינה," beino le-veinah,
but it's not like a logical continuum. Something could very well not
at all be related to בינו לבינה. beino le-veinah. So the ר"ן
Ran sort of works that out and it might be a throwaway
line there. The ר"ן Ran tries to work that out. Yeah.
But so what about Rabbi Yose who is saying that our decision
then is according to Rabbi Yose?
Oh, how do we פסקן? pasken? So that's the debate in the
ראשונים. Rishonim. Once we're saying the whole סתם פרק stam perek is
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, does that mean that we פסקן pasken like
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose or not? So a lot of ראשונים Rishonim
say we don't, like you could see right now. The very fact
that we wanted to know what would the רבנן Rabbanan say about
sex, what was שמואל's Shmuel whole statement about who is the provider?
Right? Everybody is talking with the רבנן Rabbanan while saying that the
סתם משנה stam mishna is רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose, right? So that,
it's not necessarily true that we פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי. Rebbe
Yose. Good reason to think that we don't. Okay.
Then nevertheless, you know, רבי Rebbe or whoever was the editor of
this פרק perek over here wanted to סתם stam like רבי יוסי,
Rebbe Yose, we should think then it means he holds like that.
Well, it wasn't סתם-סתם, because he said דברי רבי יוסי. divrei Rebbe
Yose. So it was רבי יוסי'ס Rebbe Yose's position, but he wasn't
saying it as סתם.
stam But it's in the middle of a I don't know.
So okay, that's why there's a מחלוקת machlokes how we פסקן. pasken.
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Another
statement of שמואל. Shmuel.
Okay, Jonathan, this is going to get to your point. So okay,
and this is going to be fun. A little bit more anyway,
a little different. נדרה משתי ככרות. Nadra mishtei kikarot.
She says, "These two loaves are forbidden to me." Now, one of
them is this nice, fresh, delicious white bread. The other is this,
you know, multi-grain heavy- I'm just teasing. Anyway, but it's some type
of a bread that is not a big deal not to eat.
Let's just say it's stale. Okay. באחת נתענה. Be-achat nit'aneh. The-
I think multi-grain, because the ראשונים Rishonim say like one is fine
white bread and the other is like bran. Anyway, באחת נתענה, be-achat
nit'aneh, one of them is a type of an ענוי inui not
to be able to eat this like good white bread. Okay, באחת
אין נתענה, be-achat ein nit'aneh, the other is like, eh, big deal,
I don't like bran bread anyway, or it's stale. So half of
her נדר neder is ענוי נפש, inui nefesh, half of it is
not. Okay. So by the way, notice like how big of a
deal is it not to have one loaf of bread? Have a
different loaf of bread, right? So again, it seems like once, you
know, it's about food, even though the scope is very narrow, somehow
that becomes ענוי נפש. inui nefesh. Okay. Now, באחת אין נתענה, be-achat
ein nit'aneh, but nevertheless for one bread that's denying- like not having
that bread, that's no big deal. Okay. Now, מתוך שהוא מפר למתענה
מפר לשאינו מתענה. mitoch shehu mefer le-mit'aneh, mefer le-she-eino mit'aneh.
Because the husband can מפר mefer for the one that he that
is about denial, he can מפר mefer for both of them. Now,
what's the logic for this? So my my gut would have been
to say that it's sort of like exactly what Jonathan asked before,
like, you know, we have a principle of נדר שהותר מקצתו הותר
כולו. neder she-hutar mikzato hutar kulo. So what about the principle of
הופר? hufar? Would we say נדר שהופר מקצתו הופר כולו? neder she-hufar
mikzato hufar kulo? You know, if one נדר- neder she didn't say,
"I'm אסור assur for this loaf," and then she said, "I'm אסור
assur for that loaf." That's a different story. She said, "Those two
loaves אסורה עלי." asurah alai. So it's one נדר, neder, right? And
if it's one נדר neder and you- so if you מפר mefer
part, maybe the whole thing falls away. The problem with saying that,
Jonathan, is as we saw just a minute ago, that's not the
הלכה. halacha. We see before that the husband could be מפר חלקו
mefer chelko by the case of תשמיש tashmish and not other people's.
So it doesn't seem to be the הלכה. halacha. So
the
way- the ר"ן'ס Ran's answer, which doesn't actually get to the reason
the husband is different, but, you know, well, let's worry about the
case for מפר חלקו mefer chelko in a minute. One way to
understand it is it just happens automatically. It's all one thing and
if you remove part of it the whole thing falls away like
הותר מקצתו הותר כולו. hutar mikzato hutar kulo. No, that's one way
of understanding what it's saying. Okay, what the ר"ן Ran says is
different. It's sort of like it gets to the same idea from
a different perspective. The ר"ן Ran says, you know, since the גמרא
Gemara says later on that you basically, you know, you have to
be
מפר mefer the whole נדר. neder.
So let's say, for example, it was not a case where one
was out of the category because it was about other people like
the case before about the sex or it was some of it
wasn't about ענוי. inui. Let's say she basically said הנאת רחיצה אסורה
עלי hana'at rechitza asurah alai
and he said, "I'm going to be מפר mefer that for the
next two days, but not the rest of it," or something like
that. Okay.
So all right, so like tomatoes and no fruit, but fine.
Okay. So can that work? And the גמרא Gemara basically says later
it can't work. That basically you have to be- you know, it's
like- it learns out from the פסוק pasuk that it basically says
כל- kol he has to be מפר mefer the whole thing. He
can't just choose I'm only going to be מפר mefer part of
it and not the whole thing. Okay, so either the whole thing
or nothing. You can't just say this I'm מפר mefer for three
days or these fruits and not those fruits. Okay. So now the
ר"ן Ran says here's how the logic works.
Since the תורה Torah says you got to do all, you can't
do partial. Right now half of it is a case of ענוי
נפש, inui nefesh, the other is not. So basically we have two
choices. The choice could either be we could tell you that- so
you shouldn't be able to do it all because you only have
power about half. So we should- on the one hand we could
say, so since your only choices are all or nothing, you can
either say nothing or you could say all. Right? So either we
say nothing and I'm sorry since you can't do half of it
you can't do any of it because you got to do the
whole thing and if you can't do half you can't do any.
Or we could say since you should be entitled to do half
we're going to therefore make it possible for you to do the
whole thing because you got to be able to do either all
or nothing. So the ר"ן Ran says like that's the position here.
The position is that since ultimately you have to have the ability
to be מפר mefer those things that are of ענוי נפש inui
nefesh in this case since you would only be able to have
that ability if you were empowered to do the whole thing we
have to assume that you are empowered and do the whole thing.
The ר"ן Ran *Ran* sort of says more it's like, no, you
directly have to be empowered because actually your act of הפרה hafara
*hafara* has to be an act on the whole thing. Now, one
way or the other, we have to get back to the earlier
case where she says where he says נטולה אני מן היהודים *netula
ani min hayehudim*, where where he says where the case of sex,
where it's not the whole thing, it's just his part. How does
that work? So the ר"ן *Ran* says here's basically the difference. The
difference is, is that that's about בינו לבינה *beino lveina*. Remember we
said that was the whole point? That was about בינו לבינה *beino
lveina*. If it's about בינו לבינה *beino lveina*, right, we sort of
saw this before, the same way that his הפרה *hafara* בינו לבינה
*beino lveina* doesn't extend to her next marriage. That's not like he's
totally undoing it. בינו לבינה *beino lveina* is basically saying, hey, this
impacts me, I get to have a vote here, I get to
override. So בינו לבינה *beino lveina* is by its very nature much
more, you know, not about the entire נדר neder *neder* and you
know the whole thing, it's more like to the degree that it
affects me, it's not going to be binding. So it's right, and
it won't but after the divorce, for example, it remains, you know,
if she gets remarried, it kicks back in, right? Remember that, right?
So since it's basically a type of a override due to my
rights and our relationship, so it's not working on the whole נדר
neder. *neder*, it's not fundamentally removing the whole נדר neder, *neder* and
therefore it can work partially and the other part still remains. But
something that's a basic הפרה *hafara* of עינוי נפש *inuy nefesh*, that's
about completely just saying, you know, it's not because I'm a נוגע
בדבר *nogaya b'davar*, even if I'm not a נוגע בדבר *nogaya b'davar*,
even if it doesn't hurt me, right, it's just about me completely
removing it and therefore it's a type of an all or nothing.
Does he need to relearn that the same thing is הקמה *hakama*?
What? If you if you make them הקמה *hakama*, does not מיפר
*meifer* it? Like if you make them הקמה *hakama*, does it automatically
mean you make them the whole thing? כן *ken*?
Yeah, I don't remember. I mean, it's a good question. I mean,
I'm just
I don't think we covered it yet, I'd have to I'd have
to check. All right, so let's take a look. So that's the
חידוש *chidush*.
Yes, and since this case really is it's not something that's going
into effect anyway because she's married and she can't have sex with
any
other guy anyway.
Right, in in that case, so it's not really as if she's
a moved...
Right, right, that's true. It is future oriented, so maybe it's also
makes it a little bit less like you have to deal with
the whole thing right now, right?
And she could get that revoked, right, if
she would go and say... Well, she could always do a התרה
*hatara*, that's true. Yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, ואסקמה רבי יוחנן *v'askamrei d'Rabbi Yochanan*. Then רב אסי *Rav
Assi* said in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, no, מיפר
למתענה ואין מיפר לשאינו מתענה *meifer l'mitaneh v'aino meifer l'sheino mitaneh*. It
only works for the part that's עינוי *inuy*, it does not work
for the other half of it. Okay, ואיכא דאמרי *v'ika d'amrei*, and
some say בעי מיניה רב אסי מרבי יוחנן *ba'ei minei Rav Assi
me'Rabbi Yochanan*. רב אסי *Rav Assi* asked רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, נדר
neder משתי ככרות *neder mi'shtei kikarot*. She took a vow. באחת מתענה
ובאחת אינו מתענה *b'achat mitaneh u'vachat eino mitaneh*, מהו *ma hu*? What's
the story? אמר ליה *amar lei*, and he said back to him,
מיפר למתענה ואין מיפר לשאינו מתענה *meifer l'mitaneh v'aino meifer l'sheino mitaneh*.
That it was a response to a question, but it's still the
same position. According to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, it could only works
for the one that she's מתענה *mitaneh*, it's not work does not
work for the other one. איתיבי *eitivei*, I'll object on this. האשה
שנדרה בנזיר *ha'isha shenadra b'nazir*, והיתה שותה יין ומטמאה למתים *v'hayta shotah
yayin u'metama l'metim*,
a woman make a vow to be a נזיר nazir *nazir* and
she went and she started violating it. הרי זו סופגת ארבעים *harei
zo sofeket arbaim*, she gets lashes. That's pretty obvious. Moving on though,
the real point about this is the next line. הפר לה בעלה
והיא לא ידעה שהפר לה *heifer la ba'ala v'hi lo yada sheheifer
la*, the husband annulled it for her and she did was not
aware that he had annulled it. והיתה שותה יין ומטמאה למתים *v'hayta
shotah yayin u'metama l'metim*, and she was going around and in her
mind willfully violating the נזיר nazir *nazir*. אינה סופגת ארבעים *eina sofeket
arbaim*, she doesn't get lashes, cause no matter what she thought and
you know and her the fact that in her mind she was
violating it and willfully, objectively there was no נזירות nezirus. *nezirus* and
there was nothing she violated. That's the משנה *Mishnah*. Now the גמרא
*Gemara* has the following question. ומטמאה למתים אינה סופגת ארבעים *u'metama l'metim
eina sofeket arbaim*. מי אמרת *mi amarta* מיפר למתענה ואין מיפר לשאינו
מתענה *meifer l'mitaneh v'aino meifer l'sheino mitaneh*, if you say that he
can sort of do it partially, so for the stuff that's עינוי
נפש *inuy nefesh* and not for the אינו עינוי נפש *eino inuy
nefesh*, דילמא מיין דאיכא צערא הפר לה מחרצן ומזג דלא הפר לה
*dilma miyayin d'ika tzaara heifer la, mikartzan u'mizag d'lo heifer la*. One
minute, if he annulled the נזירות nezirus *nezirus*, maybe he should only
be entitled to annul the נזירות nezirus *nezirus* for the I know
but let's have let's hear them hear the question. Maybe he should
only be entitled to annul that aspect of the נזירות nezirus, *nezirus*
that causes עינוי נפש *inuy nefesh*. What's the aspect that causes עינוי
נפש *inuy nefesh*? The denial of wine. Interesting, I don't know, does
not being מטמאה למתים *metama l'metim* also call some... anyway, but the
denial of wine. Saying that I can't have a grape skin or
a grape pit, okay, well fine, but that's not עינוי נפש *inuy
nefesh*. Now that's again interesting, right? But that would sort of be
like the case of the bran bread. Not all food is עינוי
נפש *inuy nefesh*, you know, there's food that people want to eat
and food that they don't so much want to eat. Stuff that
they don't so much want to eat is not in the עינוי
נפש *inuy nefesh*. So maybe he could annul it and she would
still remain forbidden on grape pits and therefore you could have a
scenario where she could still get מלקות *malkus* even after he did
the annulment because of the part of נזירות nezirus. *nezirus* that isn't
עינוי נפש *inuy nefesh*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says the obvious answer
which is
דהא לאו צערא. She has no צער tzaar from not having grape
skins and pits. ותיסבר כרבי? v'tisbar k'Rabbi? Let her get lashes. So
אמר רב יוסף: amar Rav Yosef: אין נזירות לחצאין. ein nezirus l'chatzoim.
No, you don't have half a נזירות. nezirus Like, for example, similar
to this whole thing of half or whole. Let's say a person
says, "I am a נזיר nazir just regarding wine." Okay? So there's
two possibilities. You know what the two possibilities are about what this
person said?
Either he made a נדר neder,
not to have wine, he's not—No, he didn't make a נדר. "I'm
a נזיר nazir just regarding wine. I'm a נזיר nazir just for
טומאת מת." tumas meis.
He didn't say anything.
Either he didn't say anything, so it's or, or
he's
a נזיר nazir for the whole thing. But there is not the
possibility that he's just a נזיר nazir. for wine. נזירות nezirus, is
a package. Okay? It's all or nothing. So therefore, if she could
be מפר meifer the נזירות nezirus. in this case, nothing else do
we say is a package. It is possible to just be אסורה
asura on white bread and not on bran bread. That's a possible
end result. So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan will say when that's a
possible end result, your power only extends to the part that's about
ענוי נפש. inoy nefesh. But by נזירות, nezirus there's no end result
of a half נזירות. nezirus. So therefore in that case, if you
manage to undo part of it, you undo the whole thing. There
is one big package deal, but everywhere else it's not a package
deal. Okay, let's just end this thought and with this we'll end
today even more ahead. אמר ליה אביי. amar lei Abaye. So אביי
Abaye completely agrees, but somehow he felt רב יוסף Rav Yosef didn't
articulate it as precisely as he could have. אמר ליה אביי, amar
lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said: הקרבן לחצי נזירות איכא? hakorban l'chatzi
nezirus ika? When you say אין נזירות לחצאין, ein nezirus l'chatzoim, it
sounds like
נזירות nezirus? doesn't—you can't have a half of a נזירות, nezirus. but
it could be a half of a duration of a נזירות. nezirus
What would be the case? A woman said "I'm a נזיר" and
she did a נזירות nezirus for fifteen days and then her husband
annulled it. Now she did fifteen days? No, you can't. That's אביי's
Abaye question. And then her husband annulled it. Now remember, when the
husband annuls, it doesn't retroactively undo it, it just means it stops
now. So now she did fifteen days of a נזירות. nezirus. That
should be as a real נזיר. That doesn't stop being true. Okay.
Can she now bring the קרבן korban for doing half of the
duration of the נזירות? And the answer is no. You need to
do the full duration. So אביי Abaye just felt that רב יוסף
Rav Yosef should have articulated it a little bit better.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said there's no such thing as a half
נזירות. Okay, that's that the quality of the נזירות isn't half. But
he says but the duration also can't be half. Okay, which רב
יוסף Rav Yosef wouldn't disagree with, but אביי Abaye wanted to spell
out. אלא אמר אביי, ela amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says: אין
נזירות לחצאין בין קרבן לחצי נזירות. ein nezirus l'chatzoim bein korban l'chatzi
nezirus.
You can't have a half נזירות and you can't have basically a
half duration of a נזירות. Okay. So basically, when the husband annuls
it, a) even if he only—even though he should only have been
able to annul the wine part, it all gets annulled and b)
once it stops in the middle of its tracks, she's not going
to bring a קרבן korban either because she never completed it. And
we still have the debate of whether when you're מפר meifer part
of a נדר, does the whole נדר go away? Either you could
look at it as הותר מקצתו הותר כולו, hutar miktzaso hutar kulo,
that just naturally the rest of it falls away because once you've
been מפר meifer part—or the way the ר"ן says it is: no,
your act of הפרה has to be on the whole נדר, so
maybe therefore you should be empowered to do it all to—in order
to empower you to do part of it. That's what שמואל Shmuel
says, whereas רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says: no, your power is complete
over the part that you have power over. The part that is
ענוי נפש, inoy nefesh, you are annulling all of it and that's
what you have power over and the rest remains standing and does
not change. Okay. Good.